Guide to the Edward Eliscu Papers MS 040
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Edward Eliscu Papers
1969-1998, (Bulk 1971-1990)
1971-1990
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Eliscu, Edward, 1902-1998.
MS 040
5.5 Linear Feet, 4 boxes
Edward Eliscu, actor, lyricist, playwright, screen and songwriter, producer, and director was born in New York City on April 26, 1902. The collection consists of correspondence, clippings, scripts, lyrics, music, and other writings.
Provenance
Provenance unknown
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Edward Eliscu, actor, lyricist, playwright, screen and songwriter, producer, and director was born in New York City on April 26, 1902.
Growing up in New York he attended public schools and developed a love for music and acting as a young boy. After receiving his Bachelor of Science degree from the City College of New York, he began his acting career in 1924 when he appeared in Quarantine with Helen Hays on Broadway.
In 1929, Eliscu produced his first Broadway score with composer Vincent Youmans and co-lyricist Billy Rose entitled Great Day! Hits from this score include "Great Day," "More than Your Know" and "Without a Song." Eliscu was also widely recognized as a talented playwright and screenwriter. His screenplays created the films The Gay Divorcee, Three Husbands and Out of the Blue.
Throughout his career, Eliscu collaborated with many composers including Vincent Youmans, Billy Rose, Jay Gorney, Henry Myers, John Green, Gus Kahn, Vernon Duke, Manning Sherwin, Richard Myers, Ned Lehac and Billy Hill.
In 1930, Eliscu began contributing songs to film scores as well as writing film screenplays. His most notable film score was the 1934 Fred Astaire vehicle Flying Down to Rio. The Eliscu song "Carioca" not only launched the partnership of Fred Astaire and his co-star Ginger Rogers, but also earned Eliscu an Academy Award nomination in 1935 for Best Song.
In the late 1940s, Eliscu was blacklisted by both the motion picture and television industries because he was a recruiter for the Screen Writers Guild, attended foreign films, and was seen buying a copy of The Nation (magazine).
Eliscu was president of the American Guild of Authors & Composers from 1968 to 1973 and later inducted into the Songwriters Hall of Fame. In 1987, he received the ASCAP/ Richard Rodgers Award for his outstanding contribution to the American musical theater.
Edward Eliscu died in Newtown, Connecticut, on June 18, 1998.
Sources:
Songwriters Hall of Fame, (http://www.songwritershalloffame.org)
ASCAP Ace Database (www.ascap.com)
ASCAP Biographical Dictionary, 3rd Edition. Copyright 1966.
Scope and Content Note
The collection comprises 1.25 linear feet and two oversized boxes of material and is arranged alphabetically in one series. It consists of correspondence, clippings, scripts, lyrics, music, and other writings. The bulk of the collection are the production documents from entitled Rewind and Play. A Retrospective Revue of the Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu, which showcased Eliscu's 60 years in the theater. Elicu personally introduced most of the songs and sketches in Rewind and Play to set the mood and to explain his lyrics.
Rewind and Play. A Retrospective Revue of the Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu was performed at Western Connecticut State College in 1975. James Furman, of the music faculty, composed two new songs for the Revue: Handbook For The Virgin Voter, and Hey, Mr. Jefferson! with lyrics by Eliscu. Richard Reimold, of the Communications and Theatre Arts Department, directed the production.
Subsequent productions were called The Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu performed in Connecticut at the Bethel Gallery, Cyrenius Booth Library, and the Westport White Barn. In 1989, another musical revue, With or Without A Song, was performed at Western Connecticut University. Eliscu narrated the show as well as performed some of the songs.
Eliscu and his wife, Stella, were concerned with local, as well as national issues, and took part in the Newtown Area Forum for Action (NAFA). Information on NAFA can be found in the clippings files.
Additional information concerning Eliscu's life and career can be found in the following:
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic.
[ORGANIZATION] The files are grouped into 1 series.
Missing Title
Inventory
Related Material
http://www.nyu.edu/library/bobst/research/tam. Guide to the Edward Eliscu Papers, 1938--1998.
Eliscu, Edward. With or Without A Song, A Memoir. Maryland: Scarecrow Press. Inc., 2001.
Blacklisting -- United States.; Dramatists, American -- 20th century -- Biography.; Audiotapes.; Lyricists-United States -- Biography.; Screenwriters -- United States -- Biography.; Posters; Sheet music.; Scripts (documents).; Photographs.; Scores.; Cole, Lester, 1904--1985; Eliscu, Edward, 1902-1998.; Furman, James, 1937-1989
- Inventory
  - The American Guild of Authors and Composers (ARSC), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - An Evening with Edward Eliscu (92nd Street YM/YMHA, Lyrics and Lyricists Series) February 26, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
  - An Evening with Edward Eliscu (92nd Street YM/YMHA, Lyrics and Lyricists Series) February 26, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Association for Recorded Sound Collections (ARSC), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1969-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Clippings, 1969-1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cole, Lester, Memorial Meeting, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9a)
  - Correspondence, 1960s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cyrenius Booth Library Performance, April 12, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Eliscu Album-Outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Eliscu Memorial, September 13, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fair Exchange, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fair Fields Magazine, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - It's 11:59, White Barn Theater, Westport, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3-8)
  - It's 11:59, White Barn Theater, Westport, 1980 (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Hey, Mr. Jefferson, undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - The Kelly Green Motel, undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - 1776, undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - The Virgin Voter, undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Lyrics, Music, Scripts, and Literary Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 16-53)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Music Score: Fair Exchange, undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: Fair Exchange (c.2), undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: Fair Exchange (c.3), undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: Golden Ladder, undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: My Right Hand Doesn't Know, undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: My Right Hand Doesn't Know, (c.2), undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: Nice Girl Blues, undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: Say No More, undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: Say No More, (c.2), undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: Ta, Ta, Old Bean, undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: Time for a Change, undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: Two Miles Out of Town, undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Music Score: Unemployment Line, undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Photographs: 13 - 5x3½ color images of Rewind and Play, May 1975 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Photographs: 1 - 4x4 color image "Portrait of Eddie", undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Photographs: 1 - 5x7 color image of Harpo Marx and Pauline Stewart. "Got It Made Ford Industrial Film", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Photographs: 1 - 8x10 b/w image of Gloria Swanson and Carey Grant. Screenwriters Guild Awards, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Play Notes, etc., 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 59-60)
  - Play Notes, etc., 1974-1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Poster: Rewind and Play, WCSC (2c), 1975 (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Poster: With or Without a Song, WCSU, 1990 (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Poster: The Rimes & Times of Edward Eliscu, Bethel Gallery, Edition (3c), 1978 (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Reference Material, Newtown, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Rewind and Play. A Retrospective Revue of the Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu. Playing Script, Western Connecticut State College, May 1975. (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Rewind and Play. A Retrospective Revue of the Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu. Playing Script, Western Connecticut State College, May 1975. (c.2) (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Rewind and Play. A Retrospective Revue of the Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu. Rehearsal Script, Western Connecticut State College, May 1975 (Box 1, Folder 64-65)
  - Rewind and Play. A Retrospective Revue of the Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu. WCSC, "It's No Fun Eating Alone" (music & lyrics), May 1975. (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play. A Retrospective Revue of the Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu. (Clippings) Western Connecticut State College, May 1975. (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Rewind and Play, A Retrospective Revue of the Rimes And Times of Edward Eliscu, undated (Box 1, Folder 67-68)
  - Rewind and Play, A Retrospective Revue of the Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu (c.2), undated (Box 1, Folder 69-70)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn, undated (Box 2, Folder 10-15)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: Dora Flora Sextette (music), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: Hey, Mr. Jefferson (music & lyrics), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: The House That Hartford Built (music & lyrics), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: The House That Hartford Built (music & lyrics) c.2, undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: I'm Just a Stranger In Town (music), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: Knife, Why Are We There, Mc Knows Why (partial music), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: Springtime in Kusmin (music), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: Stranger In Town (music), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: Twenty-five Bucks (p. 5 only), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: Without a Song (music and lyrics), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play (Four From One) White Barn: Without A Song, (p.2-5), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Rewind and Play, (edited script), undated (Box 1, Folder 71-73)
  - Richard Rodgers Award, November 11, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu, Westport White Barn, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 74-79)
  - Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu, Westport White Barn, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu, Bethel Gallery, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 80-85)
  - Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu, Bethel Gallery 1978 (music) (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Rimes and Times of Edward Eliscu (script), undated (Box 1, Folder 86-89)
  - Sheet Music: Crispus Attucks from The New Meet the People, undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Sheet Music: Happy Because I'm In Love from Great Day, undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - Sheet Music: Hear Me from The Dagger and The Rose (5 pages, back cover missing), undated (Box OS 2, Folder *)
  - The Song Writers Showcase (audiotape), 1995 (Box OS 1, Folder *)
  - Meet The People, 1990-01-01 (Box OS 1, Folder *)
    General
    Eight songs by Gorney, Myers, and Eliscu; from phonograph recordings
  - With Or Without A Song, (clipping), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 90)